So, now, let's talk about IAM conditions
Bây giờ, hãy nói về các IAM condition
and what they can imply for your policies.
và ý nghĩa của chúng đối với policy.
So, just so you know, they apply to policies within IAM.
Chúng áp dụng cho các policy trong IAM,
So that could be for policies for users,
có thể là policy cho user,
that could be policies for your resource policies,
policy dạng resource policy,
for example, for your S3 buckets,
ví dụ cho S3 bucket,
or that could be endpoint policies, and so on.
hoặc endpoint policy, v.v.
So, really, anything.
Nói chung là rất rộng.
So the first one is aws:SourceIP.
Đầu tiên là aws:SourceIP.
And this is used to restrict the client IP
Dùng để hạn chế IP client
from which the API calls are being made.
từ đó các API call được thực hiện.
So if we look at this one right here,
Ví dụ ở đây,
it has a Deny star on everything
có Deny * trên mọi thứ
if it's not an IP address.
nếu không phải đến từ các IP cho phép.
And then we have a list of two CIDRs,
Và ta có danh sách hai CIDR,
of two IP address ranges.
hai dải địa chỉ IP.
So that means that unless the client makes an API call
Nghĩa là trừ khi client gọi API
from within these IP addresses,
từ trong các dải IP này,
then the API call is being denied.
thì API call sẽ bị từ chối.
And this can be used, for example,
Cách này có thể dùng, ví dụ,
to restrict usage on AWS only to, for example,
để giới hạn việc sử dụng AWS chỉ từ
your company network and, therefore, guaranteeing
mạng nội bộ công ty, nhờ đó đảm bảo
that only your company can access your own AWS environment.
chỉ công ty bạn mới truy cập được môi trường AWS của mình.
So that's one of these conditions.
Đó là một condition.
Then we have aws:RequestedRegion.
Tiếp theo là aws:RequestedRegion.
So this is, again, something global
Đây là key ở phạm vi AWS (toàn cục)
because it started at the AWS,
và dùng để hạn chế region mà API gọi tới.
and it's restricting the region the API calls are made to.
Trong ví dụ này, ta deny mọi thao tác trên EC2, RDS, DynamoDB
So in this one we deny anything on EC2, RDS, and DynamoDB
nếu region là eu-central-1 hoặc eu-west-1.
if we are in the region eu-central-1 or eu-west-1.
Tức là ta từ chối truy cập các dịch vụ này ở các region cụ thể.
Okay, so here we deny access to these services
Và có thể áp dụng rộng hơn
in the specific regions.
ở Organizations bằng SCP
And this can be applied more globally
để deny/allow chỉ một số region nhất định.
on their organization SCP to deny or to allow
Tiếp theo là ec2:ResourceTag.
only access to a specific region.
Như bạn thấy, tiền tố là EC2
So, as you can see now, the prefix of this tag is EC2,
nên điều này áp vào tag của EC2 instance.
therefore, this applies to the tags on your EC2 instance.
Ở đây, ta allow Start/Stop instance
And, so, here we allow to start and to stop instances, okay,
cho bất kỳ instance nào nếu ResourceTag/Project
for any instance if the ResourceTag/Project
bằng DataAnalytics.
is equal to DataAnalytics.
Nghĩa là nếu EC2 instance có tag phù hợp
So that means that if the EC2 instance has the correct tags,
gồm Project: DataAnalytics thì được phép.
being Project and DataAnalytics, then we're good.
Ngoài ra có aws:PrincipalTag
But then, as you can see, there is the aws:PrincipalTag,
áp vào tag của user (principal), không phải tag của EC2.
and this applies to your user tag, okay.
User của bạn cũng phải thuộc
So it's not an EC2 instance tag, this is a user tag.
department: data để thực hiện các action này.
And, so, your user must also be part
Có aws:MultiFactorAuthPresent
of the department data to perform these actions.
để bắt buộc xác thực đa yếu tố (MFA).
We have aws:MultiFactorAuthPresent
Bạn có thể xem ví dụ: user có thể làm mọi thứ trên EC2,
to force multifactor authentication.
nhưng chỉ được Stop/Terminate instance
So you can have a look at it.
nếu MFA hiện diện
But the user can do anything on EC2,
(MultiFactorAuthenticationPresent),
but they can only stop and terminate instances
nên ta có deny khi điều kiện này bằng false.
if they have MultiFactorAuthenticationPresent,
Giờ hãy xem một IAM policy cho S3 bucket.
so this is a deny on the false.
Đây là bucket policy, với hai statement.
Now let's have a look at an IAM policy for your S3 buckets.
Statement đầu là ListBucket,
So this is a bucket policy, and we have two statements.
áp dụng cho ARN s3:::test ở đây.
And the first one is a ListBucket,
Vì đây là quyền ở cấp bucket
and this applies to this arn right here, so s3:::test.
nên ta phải chỉ định chính bucket đó.
Because it's a bucket level permission
Còn GetObject, PutObject,
and, therefore, we have to specify the bucket itself.
DeleteObject áp dụng cho object trong bucket
But if we have a look at GetObject, PutObject,
nên ARN sẽ khác,
and DeleteObject, this applies to objects within a bucket
và bạn dùng /* để biểu diễn
and, therefore, your arn is going to be different,
tất cả object trong bucket.
and you're going to have /* to represent
Đây là lý do ARN khác nhau:
all the objects within your buckets.
quyền ở cấp object.
And this is why you have a different arn here
Điều này có thể xuất hiện trong kỳ thi.
because this is an object level permission.
Giờ hãy xem resource policy
And, again, this is something that can come up in the exam.
và aws:PrincipalOrgID.
Now let's have a look at the resource policies
Condition aws:PrincipalOrgID
and the aws:PrincipalOrgID.
có thể dùng để giới hạn resource policy
So this condition right here, the aws:PrincipalOrgID,
chỉ cho các tài khoản là thành viên của một AWS Organization.
can be used to restrict resource policies
Giả sử ta có một organization với nhiều tài khoản
to only accounts that are a member of an AWS organization.
và một S3 bucket có policy như thế này.
So we have an organization with multiple accounts,
Policy cho phép PutObject hoặc GetObject
and say we have S3 buckets with this policy on it.
chỉ khi API call được thực hiện từ một tài khoản
And it's saying that you can do a PutObject or a GetObject
có PrincipalOrgID tương ứng.
only if the API call is made from an account
Vì vậy chỉ các member account trong organization của bạn
that has the PrincipalOrgID of whatever.
mới truy cập được S3 bucket;
And, therefore, it's only going to allow member accounts
mọi user bên ngoài organization sẽ bị từ chối
from your organization to access the S3 bucket,
do bucket policy này.
but any user outside the organization will be denied
Bạn vừa xem nhiều condition khác nhau trong IAM policy,
because of this S3 bucket policy.
hy vọng đã rõ ràng và giúp bạn tinh chỉnh use case
Okay, so you've seen a lot of different conditions
để xây dựng các tình huống bảo mật nâng cao.
in now your IAM policies, but hopefully that makes sense,
Vậy là xong. Hẹn gặp bạn ở bài tiếp theo.